<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-04T19:39:59+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Treangen lab at Rice University</title><subtitle>Treangen lab website. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Science at Home: A Summer of Bioinformatics in Ghana</title><link href="/blog/2025/ExpandingHorizonsGhana/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science at Home: A Summer of Bioinformatics in Ghana"/><published>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/ExpandingHorizonsGhana</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/ExpandingHorizonsGhana/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Hi, my name is <a href="https://treangenlab.com/profiles/nkokroko/">Natalie Kokroko</a>, a 2nd-year PhD student in the Computer Science Department at Rice University. My research focuses on developing and applying computational tools for microbiome and metagenomic sequencing data analysis. As someone who grew up in Ghana and now conducts advanced research in the U.S., returning home not just for vacation but to foster scientific collaboration was a fulfilling experience. It felt like weaving together two worlds I love, home and science.</p> <p>I was excited for the opportunity to contribute to the growing bioinformatics scene in Ghana by spending part of my summer at the West African Centre for Cell Biology of Infectious Pathogens <a href="https://www.waccbip.org/">WACCBIP</a> where I once was an intern in the <a href="https://www.waccbip.org/research/research-groups/genomics-and-bioinformatics-group">Genomics and Bioinformatics</a> unit.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Natalie_Ghana2025-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Natalie_Ghana2025-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Natalie_Ghana2025-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Natalie_Ghana2025.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h2> <p>Before I take you through my experience, I would like to acknowledge the <a href="https://graduate.rice.edu/expanding-horizons-fellowship-program">Expanding Horizons Fellowship</a> sponsor, Dr. Walter Loewenstern for making this dream a reality. I would also like to thank my PhD advisor, <a href="https://profiles.rice.edu/faculty/todd-treangen">Dr. Todd Treangen</a> for supporting my interest in building research connections back home, and to <a href="https://www.ug.edu.gh/bcmb/people/samuel-duodu-phd">Prof.Samuel Duodu</a> at the University of Ghana for welcoming me into his research group and exploring opportunities for collaboration.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="from-houston-to-accra">From Houston to Accra</h2> <p>From Houston to Accra, the journey was long but deeply fulfilling. It began with a 3.5-hour flight to Washington, D.C., followed by an 11-hour overnight flight across the Atlantic to Accra, Ghana. After months of planning and anticipation, I was finally home. Waiting for me at the airport were two familiar faces, my sister and our dog, Sibeau, ready with warm hugs and wagging tails.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="about-waccbip">About WACCBIP</h2> <p>The West African Centre for Cell Biology of Infectious Pathogens is a world-class biomedical research institute based at the University of Ghana, my Alma Mater. WACCBIP’s research focuses on genomic and molecular biology which involves generating lots of sequencing data: from human samples, pathogens or microbiomes. With this knowledge, I sought to apply the bioinformatics skills I have been equipped with over the course of my PhD to some data in Ghana.</p> <p>One of the first people I connected with was <a href="https://www.ug.edu.gh/bcmb/people/samuel-duodu-phd">Prof. Samuel Duodu</a> from the Department of Biochemistry at the University of Ghana. Prof. Duodu expressed a strong interest in establishing a collaboration, and we arranged meetings to discuss ongoing projects, data needs, and potential joint research directions. I also had the chance to work closely with one of his research assistants, whose focus is on building bioinformatics pipelines. Together, we compared workflows, exchanged ideas, and discussed how different computational approaches could improve analysis outcomes.</p> <p>During my first week, I had the opportunity to meet a number of the new interns from my alma mater which is University of Ghana where the research centre(WACCBIP) is located. It was a pleasure telling them about my graduate school experience and the kind of research in Bioinformatics I am currently doing. I was thrilled to see my undergraduate research advisor, <a href="https://www.ug.edu.gh/biomedical-engineering/people/prof-samuel-kojo-kwofie">Prof. Samuel Kwofie</a>, the Head of the Biomedical Engineering Department. These conversations were a key part of my visit’s capacity-building mission: inspiring early-career scientists and strengthening Ghana’s next generation of bioinformatics researchers.</p> <h2 id="the-scientific-focus">The Scientific Focus</h2> <p>During my stay,Prof. Duodu took me through some of the projects his research group is working on and the need for bioinformatics pipelines that would be able to make the projects go a long way. I was introduced to an exciting ongoing research project focused on non-malarial febrile illnesses. Cases where patients present with fever symptoms, but test negative for Plasmodium, the parasite responsible for malaria. These illnesses are often caused by a wide range of bacterial and viral pathogens, and identifying their exact etiology is crucial for effective diagnosis and treatment. The team’s approach is not just to detect pathogens, but also to understand the host’s immune response to these infections.</p> <p>They are currently working with a large collection of biological samples gathered from patients in the field. These samples, collected from individuals experiencing febrile illness but without malaria, offer a valuable resource for both host transcriptomic analysis and pathogen detection. On the pathogen side, they plan to use metagenomic sequencing to comprehensively identify the bacteria, viruses, fungi, or parasites present in the samples.</p> <p>The next step in this project involves using metagenomic sequencing to detect and identify the pathogens present in these samples. Once the sequencing is completed, the data will require a full bioinformatics pipeline; from raw read processing to taxonomic classification and downstream analysis. This is where my expertise from the <a href="https://treangenlab.com/">Treangen Lab</a> comes in.</p> <p>I introduced several tools and resources developed in the Treangen Lab, including our GitHub repositories and relevant documentation. These tools, designed for metagenomic data analysis, could be adapted to help process the sequencing data once available. I also had productive discussions with the research team about how these pipelines could fit into their analysis workflow and how future improvements could be tailored to better suit their data.</p> <p>While the sequencing phase is still in progress, we’ve laid the foundation for a strong collaborative relationship. We’ve scheduled follow-up meetings to continue developing this project, and I’m looking forward to receiving the first batches of data to begin analysis. This partnership holds strong potential for both impactful research and capacity building in genomic epidemiology and pathogen detection in Ghana.</p> <p>Excited about working with data sequenced in Ghana that is relevant to them out there. This is only the beginning of the collaboration, and I am glad I had this opportunity to establish this collaboration between my alma mater and Rice University. In the next few months, I am hoping to receive the data after sequencing in order to run some analysis which I believe will lead to a collaborative publication.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="accomplishments-this-summer">Accomplishments This Summer</h2> <ol> <li> <p>Initiated a collaboration between the Treangen Lab at Rice University and WACCBIP at the University of Ghana.</p> </li> <li> <p>Engaged in capacity building by mentoring interns and junior researchers in bioinformatics tools, workflows, and graduate school pathways.</p> </li> <li> <p>Shared computational resources (pipelines, scripts, and documentation) to support local analysis workflows.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2> <p>Although the sequencing data is not yet available, the foundation has been laid for a productive and impactful partnership. In the coming months, I will work with the WACCBIP team to process the first datasets, perform pathogen identification. We anticipate that this work will lead to joint publications and, more importantly, provide actionable insights for public health in Ghana.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-this-experience-meant-to-me">What This Experience Meant to Me</h2> <p>Being able to connect with my home country on a scientific level was not just rewarding, it was inspiring. Seeing the depth and quality of research being done at WACCBIP reinforced my belief that African-led science has a powerful role to play in global health. This trip reminded me that research is not just about data and algorithms; it’s about building bridges between countries, institutions, and people to solve problems that matter.</p> <p>I am deeply grateful to the Expanding Horizons Fellowship for making this experience possible and for supporting scholars like me in pursuing opportunities that strengthen global scientific collaboration.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Natalie Kokroko</name></author><category term="workshops"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Natalie's summer research collaboration in Ghana through the Expanding Horizon's Fellowship.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Michael Wang now Dr. Wang!</title><link href="/blog/2025/mwang/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Michael Wang now Dr. Wang!"/><published>2025-04-02T15:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-02T15:32:13+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/mwang</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/mwang/"><![CDATA[<p>Michael passed his Ph.D. defense with flying colors, congrats Michael and thank you for all of the contributions to the lab!</p> <p>Committee members:</p> <ul> <li>Dr. Todd Treangen (Rice CS)</li> <li>Dr. Omid Veiseh (Rice BIOE)</li> <li>Dr. Lauren Stadler (Rice CEVE)</li> <li>Dr. Caleb Bashor (Rice BIOE)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="labnews"/><category term="Michael"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[PhD defense]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bryce Kille now Dr. Kille!</title><link href="/blog/2025/drbryce/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bryce Kille now Dr. Kille!"/><published>2025-01-27T15:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-27T15:32:13+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/drbryce</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/drbryce/"><![CDATA[<p>Bryce passed his Ph.D. defense with flying colors, congrats Bryce and thank you for all of the contributions to the lab!</p> <p>Committee members:</p> <ul> <li>Dr. Adam Phillippy (NIH NHGRI)</li> <li>Dr. Caleb Bashor (Rice BIOE)</li> <li>Dr. Fritz Sedlazeck (BCM HGSC)</li> <li>Dr. Lydia Kavraki (Rice CS)</li> <li>Dr. Todd Treangen (Rice CS)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="labnews"/><category term="bryce"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thesis proposal defense]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections from Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomics 2024</title><link href="/blog/2024/LAMG_conference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections from Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomics 2024"/><published>2024-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/LAMG_conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/LAMG_conference/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>I am excited to share my experiences at the <a href="https://www.lamg.info/conference-site">Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomes (LAMG), 2024 Conference</a>, held from September 15th to 19th at the beautiful Lake Arrowhead. Presenting my poster on two computational tools, Lemur and Magnet, developed by Treangen lab alumni; <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=HEwzrPEAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Dr. Nicolae Sapoval</a> and <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=v39CxLgAAAAJ&amp;hl=zh-CN">Dr. Yunxi Liu</a> respectively, was a privilege. Lemur is a tool for rapid and accurate taxonomic profiling on long-read metagenomic datasets and Magnet is a computational tool that uses reference based method to refine taxonomic assignment and provide accurate abundance estimations. Find more details about these projects <a href="https://github.com/treangenlab/lemur">here</a></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posterLAMG-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posterLAMG-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posterLAMG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posterLAMG.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="first-impressions">First Impressions</h3> <p>The setting was stunning! We stayed in lakeside cabins with a serene, scenic view, and the perfect California weather made it easy to unwind, enjoy nature, and dive into productive networking and science.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/LakeArrowhead-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/LakeArrowhead-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/LakeArrowhead-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/LakeArrowhead.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>As a computational biology and bioinformatics student, it was exciting to be among a predominantly wet-lab audience, sharing insights and learning what biologists value in computational tools. I liked how there was a good mix of students and PIs and Biotech companies as well. This gave me the industry and academia interplay which I really like to see. The diverse talks were inspiring, and two stood out to me in particular.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="highlights-of-the-talks">Highlights of the Talks</h2> <p>One of the standout talks for me was <a href="https://djschwartzlab.wustl.edu/">Dr. Drew Schwartz’s</a>(https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=_eybPZYAAAAJ&amp;hl=en) presentation titled, “Pediatric Gut Microbiome Development and Disruption.” Dr. Schwartz’s work dives deep into the potential of the microbiome to inform personalized medicine—especially for vulnerable pediatric patients.Dr. Schwartz raised an interesting question: Can the composition of a newborn’s microbiome predict their risk of bloodstream infections? The goal is to explore the use of rapid long-read sequencing combined with advanced computational algorithms to conduct personalized risk assessments and support antibiotic stewardship. This approach could significantly reduce unnecessary antibiotic treatments for infants, which is a crucial step toward optimizing neonatal care.</p> <p>Another great talk “Into the Unknown: Genome-resolved Metagenomics of Soil using HiFi Sequencing,” <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=xZFaH9oAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Dan Portik</a> delved into the complexities of soil metagenome assembly and the potential of long-read sequencing to improve it. Using the latest Revio PacBio sequencer, Portik and his team tested HiFi-MAG-Pipeline to generate metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs) with high accuracy, overcoming the long-standing challenges of soil metagenome assembly. He demonstrated how short-read sequencing struggles with MAGs, whereas PacBio HiFi’s long reads can deliver transformative, scalable assemblies, marking a significant advancement in metagenomics research.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="poster-presentation-feedback">Poster Presentation feedback</h2> <p>I received positive feedback on my poster, with a lot of interest in Lemur and Magnet’s efficiency and precision. Participants appreciated how lightweight the tools were, and many were impressed by Magnet’s capability as a quality check and abundance estimation tool. There was also interest in expanding the tools to detect viral species. The networking opportunities were invaluable, especially as a “bio-heavy” conference where I could learn directly from biologists, the primary users of the tools our lab develops. Hearing from researchers who had already used Lemur was a gratifying highlight, especially when they shared how straightforward and effective it was for their analyses.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="overall-experience">Overall Experience</h2> <p>Overall, my first trip to Lake Arrowhead was a memorable experience, surrounded by beautiful mountains and lakes. Beyond the picturesque setting, this conference was a rich environment for networking and sparking new ideas. It highlights for me the collaborative nature of the microbial genomics field and the importance of continuous interactions between computational and biological perspectives. I’m excited to bring back these insights to our lab and continue contributing to the dynamic world of microbial genomics! This is a conference that anyone with an interest in microbiome studies should attend, the diverse work being done across the world in this field is mindblowing and very innovative. The remote location of Lake Arrowhead also gave me time to focus on science with no distraction.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Natalie Kokroko</name></author><category term="labnews"/><category term="workshops"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Natalie's first experience and takeaways from the Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomes Conference, 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections from MBL STAMPS 2024</title><link href="/blog/2024/stampsblog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections from MBL STAMPS 2024"/><published>2024-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/stampsblog</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/stampsblog/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Hey there, I’m Austin Marshall, a first year postdoctoral fellow in the <a href="https://villapol.hmailabs.org/">Villapol</a> and <a href="https://treangenlab.github.io/">Treangen</a> Labs where I work on trimming the knowledge gap between microbiologists and computer scientists. This blog will be related to my experience of the Strategies and Techniques for Analyzing Microbial Population Structures (STAMPS) workshop that I attended this past July.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="venue">Venue</h2> <h3 id="location">Location</h3> <p>The STAMPS workshop is held at the University of Chicago, Marine Biological Laboratory. The Marine Biological Laboratory (<strong>MBL</strong>) is located in <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Woods+Hole,+Falmouth,+MA/@41.5300117,-70.6892765,14z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m6!3m5!1s0x89e4d87731d3bb2b:0x6057f1e3e2336b81!8m2!3d41.5264977!4d-70.6730857!16zL20vMHR5N2I?entry=ttu&amp;g_ep=EgoyMDI0MDkyNS4wIKXMDSoASAFQAw%3D%3D">Wood’s Hole, Massachusetts</a> and is the closest mainland town to <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Martha's+Vineyard/@41.3923525,-70.817379,11z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m14!1m7!3m6!1s0x89e525890034153b:0xf5d72dfce4b4bc43!2sMartha's+Vineyard!8m2!3d41.3804981!4d-70.645473!16zL20vMGd0cmc!3m5!1s0x89e525890034153b:0xf5d72dfce4b4bc43!8m2!3d41.3804981!4d-70.645473!16zL20vMGd0cmc?entry=ttu&amp;g_ep=EgoyMDI0MDkyNS4wIKXMDSoASAFQAw%3D%3D">Martha’s Vineyard.</a></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/crabs_mbl-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/crabs_mbl-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/crabs_mbl-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/crabs_mbl.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="history">History</h3> <p>I was unaware of the immensely deep research history that the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and Marine Biology Laboratory have until I was tired of having my thinking cap on one evening and started looking around the amazing displays where I stumbled upon this.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/thm_nobel-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/thm_nobel-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/thm_nobel-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/thm_nobel.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Check out this awesome Nobel prize they have on display near the Lillie Library, it was awarded to Thomas Hunt Morgan for his discovery of the role chromosomes play in heredity. Countless nobel laureates, defining figures in biology, and just amazing researchers had walked through these same halls that I was fortunate enough to have the opportunity to as well. For a wild list of nobel laureates affiliated with the MBL check out <a href="https://www.mbl.edu/about/history-archives/nobel-laureates">this page.</a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="topics-and-presenters">Topics and Presenters</h2> <p>The <a href="https://www.mbl.edu/education/advanced-research-training-courses/course-offerings/strategies-and-techniques-analyzing-microbial-population-structures">course description</a> of the STAMPS workshop is pretty spot-on. (<em>nanopore sequencing pun</em>) We went through the analysis of short-read and long-read amplicon sequencing analysis as well as metagenomic sequence analysis. Personally, I believe the <em>Stats Day</em> was the most useful part for me but this could be due to my background and experience level.</p> <p>The speaker lineup for the STAMPS workshop is pretty insane. The lectures began with an introduction into sequencing modalities and 16S sequence analysis by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=zGifBvwAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Dr. Ben Callahan.</a> Following Dr. Callahan, we were introduced into metagenomics and kmer based analyses by <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=O4rYanMAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Dr. C. Titus Brown</a> who is definitely a leader in this field as his group is responsible for the creation and maintenance of <a href="https://github.com/sourmash-bio/sourmash">sourmash</a>, <a href="https://github.com/dib-lab/khmer">khmer</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/spacegraphcats/spacegraphcats/">spacegraphcats</a>.</p> <p>After Dr. Brown gave the basis of metagenomic asequencing and analysis it was time for my group to step up to the plate. My co-PI <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=N5irv88AAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Dr. Todd J. Treangen</a> and STAMPS alumni / research scientist in the Treangen Lab <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;user=E1v2MBUAAAAJ">Dr. Michael G. Nute</a> gave a very in-depth look into metagenomic assembly including a hands on demonstration of reference-based vs. de-novo assembly methods and also gave some insight into multiprocessing and how we as a class only ran our assembly on one core…</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/agm_assembler-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/agm_assembler-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/agm_assembler-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/agm_assembler.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Behind the scenes of the metagenomic assembly tutorial, shown above a cinnamon bun powered window size estimator.</p> <p>The next day we were introduced to the fascinating research of <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=yFncM6AAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Dr. Curtis Huttenhower.</a> If you are in the world of microbiome research you should be familiar with this name. Dr. Huttenhower covered a broad overview of his group’s research but dove in-depth with a few of the Biobakery’s newer tools including <a href="https://github.com/biobakery/anpan">anpan</a>, <a href="https://github.com/biobakery/halla">HAllA</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/biobakery/maaslin3">MaAsLin3</a>. This was probably one of the more intense lab sessions we had and we certainly put those Rstudio VM’s to good use.</p> <p>On the third to last day we had our <em>Stats Day</em>, led by the wonderful and talented <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;user=pFlAtDsAAAAJ">Dr. Amy Willis.</a> Dr. Willis walked the class through arguably some of the most complex and misunderstood areas of microbiome sequence analysis including relative abundances, alpha and beta diversity, as well as differential abundance analyses. Her research is certainly at the top of the field and if you are performing any microbiome analysis you should check out the <a href="https://github.com/statdivlab">StatDivLab’s github</a> for their plethora of programs that will help give you <em>confidence</em> in your results. I also want to shoutout her wonderful PhD students <a href="https://github.com/svteichman">Sarah</a>, <a href="https://github.com/shirmath">Shirley</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/MariaAVC">Maria</a> who are the next generation of microbiome stats wizards.</p> <p>My last full day was focused on metagenomic binning, with a little added flavor of strain level analysis and phylogenetics thanks to Mike Nute’s background and PhD with <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;user=pPB_WK0AAAAJ">Dr. Tandy Warnow.</a> During this lecture and lab, we walked through the steps of using common binning tools (and what they are doing) as well as ran a multiple sequence alignment using <a href="https://github.com/marbl/parsnp">parsnp2</a> with a <a href="https://github.com/marbl/gingr">gingr</a> visualization!</p> <p>One of the speakers who was unable to come because of the dang C*VID was <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=-ONw6lsAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Dr. Mike Lee.</a> Dr. Lee was still involved in this workshop as he was kind of our tech guy behind the scenes, as he had setup all our own individual compute instances (JupyterLab and Rstudio) and installed all the dependencies for the workshop labs to run smoothly. Mike Lee is someone I had really looked forward to meeting, as his website <a href="https://astrobiomike.github.io/">Happy Belly Bioinformatics</a>, was one of the main resources I used to begin my bioinformatics journey, also we worked in the same field at different NASA facilities for a while. Mike if you’re reading this <strong>hmu!</strong></p> <hr/> <h2 id="overall-experience">Overall experience</h2> <p>I think this was a great learning experience and it was hosted at a fantastic institution that has a remarkable past. Proabably my biggest gripe about this conference was the lack of air conditioning in the housing. Coming from Houston Texas, where the AC is on so much that there is a 40 degree temperature difference between inside and outside this was a bit of a challenge but it should not defer <strong>anyone</strong> from attending this workshop, it’s part of the experience.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="should-you-go">Should you go?</h2> <p><strong>Yes</strong>. If you are a biologist working on any microbiome analysis this would be a very beneficial experience for you and even if you are slightly seasoned in microbial sequence analysis like myself, I was still able to find it quite useful and gave me some more confidence to help get over the ever present <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome">imposter syndrome.</a> If you have any questions on the STAMPS workshop or on more aspects of my time at STAMPS feel free to reach out via my contact info and check out the <a href="https://github.com/mblstamps/stamps2024">STAMPS 2024 github!</a></p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Austin Marshall</name></author><category term="labnews"/><category term="workshops"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Austin's experience and recap of the STAMPS 2024 workshop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bryce Kille now a Ph.D. candidate!</title><link href="/blog/2024/bryce/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bryce Kille now a Ph.D. candidate!"/><published>2024-08-30T15:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T15:32:13+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/bryce</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/bryce/"><![CDATA[<p>Bryce passed his Thesis propsoal defense with flying colors, congrats Bryce!</p> <p>Committee members:</p> <ul> <li>Dr. Adam Phillippy (NIH NHGRI)</li> <li>Dr. Caleb Bashor (Rice BIOE)</li> <li>Dr. Fritz Sedlazeck (BCM HGSC)</li> <li>Dr. Vladimir Braverman (Rice CS)</li> <li>Dr. Todd Treangen (Rice CS)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="labnews"/><category term="bryce"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thesis proposal defense]]></summary></entry></feed>